<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>net.openvpn.openvpn3_gui_rs</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>
  <name>OpenVPN3 GUI</name>
  <summary>System tray indicator for OpenVPN3 VPN tunnels</summary>

  <description>
    <p>
      A system tray application for managing OpenVPN3 VPN tunnels on Linux.
      Written in Rust with GTK4 for better performance and lower memory usage
      compared to the Python version.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>System tray icon with dynamic status (idle, connecting, active, paused, error)</li>
      <li>VPN configuration management (import, remove)</li>
      <li>Session management (connect, disconnect, pause, resume, restart, reconnect)</li>
      <li>Desktop notifications for status changes (deduplicated, grouped per connection)</li>
      <li>Secure credential storage via Secret Service (oo7)</li>
      <li>Launch on login via XDG autostart (toggle in Preferences)</li>
      <li>Auto-connect on startup (most-recent or specific profile)</li>
      <li>Reconnect prompt on unexpected session drop</li>
      <li>Username/password, challenge/OTP, and browser-redirect authentication</li>
      <li>Tabbed session log viewer with live log streaming, per-tab search and log-level filter, filter-aware copy, and persistent window size</li>
      <li>Tabbed Preferences dialog (General / Security / Routing) for startup, notifications, intervals, timeout, stall detection, kill-switch, split-tunneling bypass CIDR editor with per-entry enable/disable, and credentials</li>
      <li>Configurable connection timeout with notification</li>
      <li>Connection stall detection — flags an idle tunnel in tray menu and icon</li>
      <li>Kill-switch — block all non-VPN traffic via nftables when a tunnel drops (requires the privileged helper package); always-visible state row (lock/unlock) in tray menu; lock indicator in session label when active; notifications on rule apply (persistent) and removal; helper-missing notification and Preferences hint; quit confirmation warns before removing rules</li>
      <li>Split tunneling — exempt specific networks from the VPN tunnel so they route over the local connection (requires the privileged helper package); configure bypass CIDRs in the Preferences Routing tab with per-entry enable/disable checkboxes; always-visible state row in tray menu; notifications on route apply and failure; symmetric IPv4/IPv6 routing with MSS clamping</li>
      <li>First-run help notification when the OpenVPN3 backend is not installed or reachable</li>
      <li>Automatic recovery when the OpenVPN3 service restarts</li>
      <li>Multiple VPN configuration support</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">net.openvpn.openvpn3_gui_rs.desktop</launchable>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/vvhungy/openvpn3-gui-rs</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/vvhungy/openvpn3-gui-rs/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/vvhungy/openvpn3-gui-rs</url>

  <provides>
    <binary>openvpn3-gui-rs</binary>
  </provides>

  <requires>
    <display_length compare="ge">360</display_length>
  </requires>

  <recommends>
    <control>pointing</control>
    <control>keyboard</control>
  </recommends>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <releases>
    <release version="0.4.1" date="2026-07-17">
      <description>
        <p>Correctness release — five pre-existing bugs, several security-relevant:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Kill-switch: disconnecting one session no longer strips firewall protection from other still-connected tunnels; a wrong-password auth-retry no longer drops the firewall mid-swap. (If rebind to a surviving tunnel can't anchor a live rule, the rules are torn down rather than left stale.)</li>
          <li>Kill-switch / bypass: the physical interface's rp_filter is now restored correctly after a network change mid-VPN (e.g. WiFi → Ethernet) instead of being left loose.</li>
          <li>Stats: Duration and Since now show real values for tunnels that were already up when the GUI launched, instead of "—".</li>
          <li>Stall auto-reconnect now respects its cooldown across a session reconnect, instead of looping against a persistently dead server every stall interval.</li>
          <li>An unexpected drop of a session that connected before the GUI saw it created now triggers reconnect/notification instead of being silently swallowed.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Internal: split credential_handler under the 800-line gate; consolidated duplicated bypass apply/teardown sequences; refactored the stats refresh helper. No behavior change beyond the fixes above.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.0" date="2026-07-16">
      <description>
        <p>Internal-only release closing the three-sprint complexity-reduction arc (S41–S43). No user-visible behaviour change; every high-cognitive-complexity hotspot in the tray app and killswitch helper has been decomposed into small, unit-tested pure functions behind thin async glue. Tagged as a minor version bump to mark the arc as a milestone rather than for any feature.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Decomposed the status-change signal loop, statistics poller, credential dialog, preferences save path, tray-action dispatch, service-restart watcher, and notification builders — each split into pure, tested helpers (71 new tests) plus thin impure wiring.</li>
          <li>Split the largest modules (stats_poller, status_handler) into concern-focused submodules under the file-size health gate.</li>
          <li>The privileged killswitch helper's rule-apply path was refactored to extract its watcher teardown; all D-Bus input-validation guards were preserved unchanged.</li>
          <li>Code review across the full arc confirmed the refactor is behaviour-preserving; pre-existing multi-session and reconnect-cooldown edge cases surfaced by the review are tracked for a future fix.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.18" date="2026-07-15">
      <description>
        <p>Internal cleanup sprint with one latency win: startup D-Bus work is parallelized and the config-name fallback is unified to a single source. No user-visible behaviour change beyond faster tray-population and consistent window titles.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Startup now runs the config scan, the session scan, and the kill-switch helper version probe concurrently (try_join), cutting startup-to-tray from the sum of the three round-trip chains to their max.</li>
          <li>Per-session cold-start reads (status, config name, config path) now run concurrently (join3) so N sessions cost N round-trips instead of 3N.</li>
          <li>The config-name fallback is centralized ("VPN Connection") so a session dropped from the tray shows the same label in the tray, notifications, Logs, and Statistics windows.</li>
          <li>The auth-retry decision is extracted into a unit-tested pure function; the two status-driven disconnect paths collapse into one helper.</li>
          <li>Micro-cleanups: reconnect delay threaded as a parameter, a trivial firewall re-apply guard inlined, and status-change dispatch returns a typed reason instead of a re-derived boolean.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.17" date="2026-07-14">
      <description>
        <p>Internal complexity-reduction sprint — the four highest cognitive-complexity hotspots (the status-change handler, D-Bus initialization, session signal handlers, and the stats poller) are decomposed into unit-tested pure helpers and thin orchestration wrappers. No user-visible behaviour change.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.16" date="2026-07-09">
      <description>
        <p>Internal quality sprint — no user-visible behaviour change.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Hardened the log viewer search filter: the lowercased-search contract is now enforced by a dedicated type, making a future caller that forgets to lowercase the search term a compile error rather than a silent case-mismatch bug.</li>
          <li>Removed three stale dead-code suppression markers whose comments had been overtaken by call sites that landed in an earlier sprint.</li>
          <li>Added unit tests for the bypass-route apply outcome mapping (success / partial / system-failure → tray state), extracted from the impure tray-and-notification wrapper.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.15" date="2026-07-08">
      <description>
        <p>Internal cleanup — no user-visible behaviour change.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Removed a dead table-presence check from the kill-switch bypass-set drift detection, simplifying the drift-diff path (helper).</li>
          <li>Reduced redundant string allocations in the log viewer search filter (lowercases the search term once per rebuild instead of once per log line).</li>
          <li>Documentation sync between the GUI and helper CIDR family-splitting helpers.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.14" date="2026-07-07">
      <description>
        <p>Split-tunneling reliability: a new drift monitor verifies the firewall bypass sets still match your configured CIDRs while a tunnel is up, plus hardening fixes found in review.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Split-tunneling drift detection — while a tunnel is connected, the app now periodically verifies the firewall bypass sets still hold your configured bypass CIDRs. If an external firewall manager, manual <code>nft</code> edit, or partial teardown removes or widens a CIDR, the tray shows a <em>Split tunnel: N CIDR(s) missing</em> (or <em>unexpected CIDR(s)</em>) warning with a persistent notification; the warning clears and a one-shot &quot;Split Tunneling Restored&quot; notice fires once the sets match again. (Requires the privileged helper package, v0.3.14+.)</li>
          <li>Host-sized bypass entries (single IPv4 or IPv6 hosts) no longer register as a permanent false drift — the comparison now treats a host's bare firewall representation and its canonical <code>/32</code>|<code>/128</code> form as the same entry.</li>
          <li>Drift notifications no longer re-fire every poll cycle while drift persists; they re-notify only when the missing or unexpected CIDR count actually changes.</li>
          <li>Internal: the status-change dispatcher's pure transition logic was extracted for unit testing, and the log viewer's search/level filter gained unit tests.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.13" date="2026-07-01">
      <description>
        <p>Credential reliability fixes closing the 0.3.11–0.3.12 arc — bug fixes only, no new features.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Saved-credential operations now unlock the keyring before every read and write, not just some of them. On a locked keyring, &quot;Remember&quot; save, per-field delete, per-config Forget, global Clear-all, and the <code>--clear-secret-storage</code> startup flag previously no-op'ed silently (save appeared to succeed but stored nothing; deletes reported nothing removed). All now act, or report a clear failure.</li>
          <li>The wrong-password auto-reconnect counter is reset when you manually Disconnect or Remove a configuration, so reconnecting with a corrected password gets the full 3 attempts again instead of inheriting the abandoned session's failures within the 5-minute window.</li>
          <li>Locked-keyring errors now show a legible &quot;Keyring is locked&quot; message on the Clear-all and Forget actions (matching the existing save path), including when the unlock prompt is dismissed, instead of raw error text.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.12" date="2026-06-30">
      <description>
        <p>Credential isolation and per-config management — finishing the saved-credential reliability work begun in 0.3.11 (no new features beyond credential handling).</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Each VPN configuration now has its own per-config <em>Forget Credentials</em> action in the tray menu (Connect → Forget Credentials → Remove), removing that connection's saved username/password without touching the configuration itself or any other connection. Previously the only way to forget saved credentials was the global "Clear all saved credentials".</li>
          <li>The 3-attempt wrong-password auto-reconnect counter is now isolated per configuration (keyed on its unique object path) instead of by display name, so wrong-password attempts on one same-named configuration no longer burn the retry budget of a sibling sharing that name.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.11" date="2026-06-29">
      <description>
        <p>Credential reliability and import feedback — hardening across saved-credential handling and config import (no new features).</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Saved credentials now pre-fill the login dialog even when the keyring (Secret Service) collection is locked: the keyring is unlocked before the dialog opens, and keyring errors are surfaced instead of silently blanking fields. A failed "remember credentials" save now shows a notification instead of no-oping silently.</li>
          <li>Saved credentials are now keyed by the VPN configuration's unique object path rather than its display name. Because OpenVPN 3 allows two configurations to share a name, keying by name could cross-wipe a same-named sibling's stored identity on removal; keying by path isolates each connection. Existing saved credentials migrate to the new key automatically on first use (the legacy entry is left intact if migration fails).</li>
          <li>Removing a VPN configuration now also wipes its stored username/password/OTP from the keyring, so rotating or deleting a connection no longer leaves orphaned credentials that could re-populate a same-named re-import with the wrong identity.</li>
          <li>Importing a configuration now validates it: a malformed file is rejected with the parser's error and removed from the profile list, instead of being silently accepted. (Requires OpenVPN 3 daemon v22+; older daemons skip validation.)</li>
          <li>Import and removal now always show an in-app result dialog, regardless of the desktop-notification setting, so a successful import is no longer silent when notifications are off.</li>
          <li>The 3-attempt auth-retry counter (wrong-password auto-reconnect cap) is now covered by unit tests.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.10" date="2026-06-26">
      <description>
        <p>Sprint 33: kill-switch fail-closed completion and one GUI correctness fix (no new features).</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The helper now restores the physical interface's rp_filter to its pre-apply value when it shuts down (SIGTERM/SIGINT). Previously a shutdown with bypass routing active left rp_filter stuck at loose mode until reboot.</li>
          <li>Re-applying bypass routes (on reconnect or bypass-list change) no longer overwrites the stored original rp_filter value, so the eventual teardown restores the true original instead of a no-op.</li>
          <li>An errored VPN session is no longer masked by the stall/idle warning icon: stall detection is now gated on the Connected status, closing a race where the stats poller re-armed the idle flag after a status transition had cleared it.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.9" date="2026-06-24">
      <description>
        <p>Kill-switch fail-closed fixes: rp_filter is now restored if bypass-route apply fails mid-chain; bypass routing is torn down when the GUI crashes (not just the firewall); re-applying rules no longer opens a no-enforcement window (the teardown and rebuild run in one atomic nft transaction).</p>
        <p>Helper hardening: nft, ip and conntrack are invoked via absolute paths so a root service never trusts ambient PATH; conntrack CIDR-flush semantics verified and documented; the routing-teardown loop cap is now tied to the single bypass-CIDR limit constant.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.8" date="2026-06-23">
      <description>
        <p>Sprint 31: GUI correctness and robustness hardening (no new features)</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Idle/stall warning now respects the configured threshold — a single zero-delta poll no longer surfaces the warning icon prematurely.</li>
          <li>Idle detection now accumulates correctly across polls — the stall timer is no longer reset every cycle, so the warning icon, idle label, and stall-driven auto-reconnect actually fire once a tunnel goes quiet past the threshold.</li>
          <li>Error state always takes priority over the idle warning — an errored session shows the error icon even if it was previously idle.</li>
          <li>Poison-tolerant locks — a panic while holding a global lock no longer bricks later disconnect and auth bookkeeping.</li>
          <li>System-bus reconnection recovery — a transient system-bus outage at startup no longer requires a GUI restart for the kill-switch helper to reconnect.</li>
          <li>Config-import dialog now routes through the shared singleton path; generic notifications route through the dedup map to prevent stacking.</li>
          <li>Internal: gsettings and log-viewer modules split for headroom under the size threshold.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.7" date="2026-05-28">
      <description>
        <p>Sprint 30: auto-reconnect, log export, statistics dialog, and split-tunnel PoC validation</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Auto-reconnect after unexpected disconnect — when enabled, the app waits a configurable delay (5–300s, default 30s) then reconnects automatically. Falls through to the existing reconnect notification if the attempt fails.</li>
          <li>Auto-reconnect on stall — a connected session that stops moving bytes past the stall threshold is now also treated as an unexpected drop when auto-reconnect is on. Cooldown window prevents reconnect loops against a permanently dead server.</li>
          <li>Log export to file — new Export button in the log viewer toolbar writes the active tab's filtered entries (respecting search and level filter) as a plain-text file for bug reports or offline analysis.</li>
          <li>Connection statistics dialog — new per-session Statistics menu item opens a live-refreshing window showing config name, status, connected-since timestamp, duration, tunnel interface, and byte counters. Auto-closes when the session disconnects.</li>
          <li>Split-tunnel PoC script — conntrack/MTU probes now target a known-reachable control host so they no longer SKIP on networks that filter the bypass destination; new test-with-killswitch command validates bypass traffic through the kill-switch; test-resume automated via D-Bus.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.6" date="2026-05-21">
      <description>
        <p>Sprint 29: dialog lifecycle hygiene, cold-start auth, and About styling</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Dialog singleton registry — Preferences, View Logs, About, and other windows now reuse a single instance instead of stacking duplicates on repeated tray clicks</li>
          <li>Modal funnel — when a confirmation dialog is open, any tray action raises the modal instead of opening a new window, preventing dead-lock behind an invisible grab</li>
          <li>Preferences is now non-modal so tray notifications remain visible while configuring settings</li>
          <li>Cold-start authentication — sessions already waiting for credentials when the GUI starts now prompt the user automatically instead of showing "Authentication required" with no dialog</li>
          <li>Unified auth dialog — all authentication flows (credentials, challenge/OTP) now route through a single 3-field dialog (username, password, authentication code) with keyring pre-fill</li>
          <li>About dialog — replaced GtkAboutDialog with libadwaita AboutWindow, fixing the blue headerbar artifact on GNOME</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.5" date="2026-05-20">
      <description>
        <p>Sprint 28: service-lifecycle robustness and per-CIDR split-tunneling status</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Connect: retry NewTunnel with exponential backoff (500 ms / 1 s / 2 s) so the first connect after a fresh login no longer fails when the openvpn3-sessions service has not yet been D-Bus activated</li>
          <li>Watcher: recover gracefully when the openvpn3-sessions service is killed — clear stale tray sessions, drop kill-switch and bypass routes at the helper, and notify the user instead of leaving zombie entries that silently reject Disconnect/Resume/Restart</li>
          <li>Split tunneling: per-CIDR success/failure reporting — tray label distinguishes "N networks" (all applied), "N active, M failed" (partial), and "Apply failed" (system-wide); a persistent notification lists up to five failing CIDRs so the user knows exactly which subnets did not route outside the tunnel</li>
          <li>Helper: ApplyBypassRoutes now returns per-entry granularity instead of failing the whole batch on the first bad CIDR; MIN_HELPER_VERSION raised to 0.3.5 to match the wire-incompatible signature change</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.4" date="2026-05-20">
      <description>
        <p>Sprint 27: split-tunneling DNS-leak documentation, build-step assertions, resume-auth diagnostics</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Docs: surface DNS-leak caveat for split tunneling in README and the Routing preferences tab — bypass routes destination IPs only, query names still hit the system resolver</li>
          <li>Docs: full code-path + failure-mode analysis of the DNS resolver path appended to docs/split-tunneling.md</li>
          <li>Diagnostics: info-level logs for resume-after-pause re-auth dispatch (session_ops, status_handler) to disambiguate the long-pause re-credential flow</li>
          <li>Build: Makefile dist targets (deb, deb-helper, rpm, rpm-helper) now assert artifact presence with ls -la after each cargo invocation — mirrors the release.yml post-conditions</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.3" date="2026-05-19">
      <description>
        <p>Sprint 26: per-entry bypass toggle, AUR helper packaging, close-out</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Split tunneling: per-entry enable/disable checkboxes in the Routing tab — suspend a bypass CIDR without losing the row</li>
          <li>Packaging: AUR PKGBUILD for the privileged kill-switch helper</li>
          <li>Packaging: removed unreferenced killswitch SVG icons from DEB/RPM assets</li>
          <li>Docs: kill-switch and split-tunneling design docs refreshed to match current code</li>
          <li>Failure modes: silent-failure tail closed as won't fix with recorded rationale</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.2" date="2026-05-19">
      <description>
        <p>Launch on login, notification improvements, release hardening</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Launch on login — XDG autostart toggle in Preferences General tab</li>
          <li>Split tunneling: per-entry enable/disable checkboxes in the Routing tab — suspend a bypass CIDR without losing the row</li>
          <li>Notifications: surface silent failures on kill-switch re-apply and menu actions</li>
          <li>Release workflow: per-step artifact assertions catch silent build failures early</li>
          <li>bump-version: awk-based prepend preserves all prior release entries</li>
          <li>Packaging: AUR PKGBUILD for the privileged kill-switch helper</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.1" date="2026-05-18">
      <description>
        <p>Patch release: CI packaging fix</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Release workflow: pre-create RPM output directory so cargo-generate-rpm produces correctly-named .rpm files (fixes v0.3.0 release shipping without RPMs)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.0" date="2026-05-18">
      <description>
        <p>Split-tunneling bypass, kill-switch hardening, and production readiness</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Split-tunneling: exempt specific networks from VPN via bypass CIDR editor (Preferences Routing tab)</li>
          <li>Kill-switch: bypass tray indicator, lock icon in session label, persistent notifications, quit confirmation</li>
          <li>Logs viewer: per-tab search and log-level filter, filter-aware copy, persistent window size</li>
          <li>GSettings schema migration smoke test for safe upgrades</li>
          <li>Connect-time failure-mode audit — silent errors now surface as notifications</li>
          <li>RPM packaging fixes (asset paths, directory entries)</li>
          <li>Version management: single source of truth from Cargo.toml, make bump-version target</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>vpn</keyword>
    <keyword>openvpn</keyword>
    <keyword>network</keyword>
    <keyword>tray</keyword>
    <keyword>indicator</keyword>
    <keyword>security</keyword>
    <keyword>privacy</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <categories>
    <category>Network</category>
    <category>Security</category>
  </categories>
</component>
